Finding Aid for A. Robert Kleiner Papers 1949-1982
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
A. Robert Kleiner Papers 1949-1982, 1961-1982
Kleiner, A. Robert
(in 16 boxes)
15.5 linear feet
Grand Rapids, Michigan, attorney and political activist. Subject files relating to his interest in state legislative apportionment, Democratic Party affairs, and Citizen Action, a Grand Rapids, Michigan, non-partisan good government organization; also photographs.
85263 Aa 2
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The collection was received from Mr. Kleiner (donor no. 7061 ) in April 1984 and April 1985.
The collection is open for research.
A. Robert Kleiner was born in Grand Rapids, Michigan, on December 2, 1916. He attended the local public schools and received his A.B. and J.D. degrees from the University of Michigan. After military service and a brief period of employment in Detroit, Kleiner returned to Grand Rapids in 1946 and became a founding partner in the law firm of Kleiner, DeYoung and Fayette. He devoted his practice almost exclusively to labor law.
Among Kleiner's civic and political activities are participation in Citizen Action, the Democratic Party, and the Commission on Legislative Apportionment. In addition, he was a charter member and director of Citizen Action, a Grand Rapids non-partisan organization for good government founded in 1949. He also served as Chairman of the Public Relations Committee in 1950 and Vice-President in 1951.
As a Democratic Party activist, Kleiner has held various offices at the county, congressional district, and state levels of the party organization, and has been a delegate to Democratic Party national conventions. An authority on legislative apportionment, Kleiner was chairman of the Michigan Democratic Party Committee on Apportionment and three-time member of the Michigan Commission on Legislative Apportionment. Twice he served as Co-chairman of the Commission, and twice he was co-author of the apportionment plan which was adopted. The Austin-Kleiner plan was adopted in 1964 and the Hatcher-Kleiner plan in 1972.
The Kleiner papers consist of approximately 15.5 feet of materials covering the years of 1949 to 1982. Most of the files are dated in the period of 1961 to 1982, however, and relate to Kleiner's interest in legislative apportionment and Democratic Party affairs. The collection came in two principal accessions, thus some file series are physically separated among different boxes.
The collection has been arranged into five series: Apportionment; Democratic Party; Photographs; Scrapbooks; and Sound Recordings.
Subjects:
Apportionment (Election law)--Michigan.; Citizen Action (Grand Rapids, Mich.); Citizens' associations--Michigan.; Democratic Party (U.S.); Grand Rapids (Mich.)--Politics and government.; Kleiner, A. Robert, 1916-; Lawyers--Michigan--Grand Rapids.; Michigan. Commission on Legislative Apportionment.; Michigan--Politics and government--1946-1960.; Michigan--Politics and government--1961-1970.
Subjects - Visual Material:
Democratic National Convention (1964: Atlantic City, N.J.); Kleiner, A. Robert, 1916-; Michigan. Commission on Legislative Apportionment.; Politics and government--1961-1970.; Politics and government--1971-1980.
Genre/Form:
Photographs.; Scrapbooks.
- Biographical
  - Miscellaneous information (Box 1)
- Apportionment
  - 1960s
    The Apportionment series is the largest and most important part of the Kleiner papers. These files have been arranged by decades (1960s, etc.) to distinguish between the apportionment debates and controversies that arise after each decennial census. Apportionment files (except for the 1960s) are further broken down into Michigan Commission on Legislative Apportionment and Democratic Party Apportionment Committee. Kleiner served on both of these bodies.
    Legislative Apportionment Commission materials consist of plans and maps, political analyses of plans, litigation files, minutes, correspondence, notes, and papers relating to public hearings and negotiations between Republican and Democratic Commissioners. The files of the Democratic Apportionment Committee consist of similar materials, but these papers were generated for and by the Democratic commissioners and state party leadership. In all cases, notes found here are Mr. Kleiner's handwritten notes on meetings, conferences, and telephone calls.
    For papers relating to apportionment in the 1960s the researcher should consult the Wilber M. Brucker collection, also available at the Bentley Library, which contain plans, minutes, and litigation proceedings. The Kleiner papers supplement, but do not duplicate, what is in the Brucker collection.
    The apportionment papers of the 1980s have major differences from the 1960s and 1970s. Although there are fewer newspaper clippings, the minutes of Commission meetings are more extensive, consisting of both summary minutes and verbatim minutes with exhibits. Computers were used in the 1980s, and analyses of the plans are in the form of computer print outs. These printouts contain extensive political and demographic data for the proposed districts.
    - Apportionment and Districting Plans
      - Submitted by Commissioners
        - Undated (Box 1)
        - 1964 (Box 1)
        - 1965, 3 folders (Box 1)
      - Submitted to Commissioners (Box 1)
      - Analyses of Plans
        - House (Box 1)
        - Senate (Box 1)
    - Clippings (Box 1)
    - Correspondence
      - 1964 (Box 1)
      - 1965 (Box 1)
      - 1966 (Box 1)
      - 1967 (Box 1)
    - Kent County Apportionment (Box 1)
    - Litigation
      - Kleiner Oral Argument (Box 1)
      - Marshall et al. vs. Hare et al 1964-1966 (Box 1)
      - Petitions and Briefs submitted to Michigan Supreme Court
        - 1964, 2 folders (Box 1)
        - 1965 (Box 1)
        - 1966 (Box 1)
      - Supreme Court Opinions
        - 1964 (Box 1)
        - 1965, 2 folders (Box 1)
        - 1966 (Box 1)
    - Notes on Meetings and Caucuses 1963-1966 (Box 2)
    - Statements of Commissioners 1965 (Box 2)
    - Transcript of Commission Meeting, December 31, 196 (Box 2)
  - 1970s
    - Commission on Legislative Apportionment
      - Apportionment and Districting Plans
        - Democratic, 5 folders (Box 2)
        - Republican (Box 2)
          Folders Nos. 1-4
        - Republican (Box 3)
          Folder No. 5
        - Plan Adopted by Commission, upon direction of Supreme Court May 24, 1972 (Box 3)
      - Correspondence/Minutes/Notes
        - January-October 1971 (Box 3)
        - November 1971-March 1972 (Box 3)
        - re: Census corrections 1971-1973 (Box 3)
      - Litigation
        - Michigan Supreme Court
          - Goebel, Huhtala, Licata, Thompson, 2 folders (Box 3)
          - Hatcher and Kleiner, 2 folders (Box 3)
          - Edwin Hughes (Box 3)
          - Virginia Selin (Box 3)
          - Kleiner Objections/Response to Goebel et al (Box 3)
          - re Kent County (Box 3)
          - Miscellaneous Briefs and Petitions (Box 3)
          - Opinions 1972 (Box 3)
        - Federal Court
          - 1973 (Box 4)
          - 1974-1975 (Box 4)
      - Minutes 1971-1972 (Box 4)
    - Democratic Apportionment Committee
      - Apportionment and Districting Plans
        - Congressional, 2 folders (Box 4)
        - Kent County, 2 folders (Box 4)
        - Party Suggestions (Box 4)
      - Correspondence/Minutes/Notes
        - 1970 (Box 4)
        - 1971 (Box 4)
        - 1972 (Box 4)
        - 1973-1976 (Box 4)
      - Drafts of Court Petitions (Box 4)
      - Miscellanea (mostly clippings) (Box 4)
      - Notes (Kleiner notes on meetings) (Box 4)
      - Political Analyses, 2 folders (Box 4)
  - 1960s-1970s
    - Scrapbooks 1963-1967, 1971-1975, 4 volumes (Box 5)
  - 1980s
    - Commission on Legislative Apportionment
      - Apportionment and Districting Plans
        - Submitted by Commissioners
          - Rosie Board (Box 6)
          - Board and Kleiner, 2 folders (Box 6)
          - Francis Brouillette, 2 folders (Box 6)
          - A. Robert Kleiner (Box 6)
          - Erma Lurvey, 2 folders (Box 6)
          - Sanderson, Daniels, Payant, Taylor, 2 folders (Box 6)
        - Submitted to Commissioners
          - William Faust (Box 6)
        - Plan published pursuant to Supreme Court Order May 21, 1982 (Box 6)
      - Apportionment Standards (Box 6)
      - Budget and Personnel (Box 6)
      - Census and Population (Box 6)
      - Correspondence
        - 1980-1982 (Box 7)
        - re Plans 1981-1982 (Box 7)
      - Litigation
        - Michigan Supreme Court
          - Petitions, Briefs, and Motions of Commissioners
            - January-March 1982 (Box 7)
            - April-May 1982 (Box 7)
          - re Bernard J. Apol Plan April-May 1982 (Box 7)
          - Southwest Detroit Committee for Fair Representation March 1982 (Box 7)
          - Coleman Young and Detroit Branch of NAACP March 1982 (Box 7)
          - Opinions March-May 1982 (Box 7)
        - Federal Court 1982, 2 folders (Box 7)
      - Minutes
        - June 1, 1981, June 19, 1981 (Box 7)
        - July 9, 1981, July 17, 1981 (Box 7)
        - July 24, 1981 (Box 7)
        - August 14, 1981, September 11, 1981, September 24, 1981 (Box 7)
        - October 9, 1981, October 16, 1981, October 23, 1981, November 6, 1981, November 20, 1981 (Box 7)
        - December 4, 1981, December 11, 1981, December 18, 1981 (Box 7)
        - January 8, 1982, January 15, 1982, January 22, 1982, January 29, 1982, February 12, 1982 (Box 7)
      - Negotiations
        - House (Box 7)
        - Senate, 2 folders (Box 8)
      - Political Analyses, 2 folders (Box 8)
      - Public Hearings 1981
        - General File (Box 8)
        - Southwest Detroit Committee for Fair Representation (Box 8)
    - Democratic Apportionment Committee
      - Apportionment and Districting Plans
        - Congressional (Box 8)
        - Kent County (Box 8)
        - Miscellaneous Maps and Plans (Box 8)
      - Audits of Plans (Box 8)
      - Clippings (Box 8)
      - Consulting Agreement (Box 8)
      - Correspondence/Minutes/Notes
        - 1975-1979 (Box 8)
        - 1980 (Box 8)
        - 1981 (Box 8)
        - 1982-1983 (Box 8)
      - Data
        - Census (Box 8)
        - Political (Box 8)
      - Notes (Kleiner notes on meetings) (Box 8)
      - Political Analyses (Box 8)
      - Political Analyses of Plans (Computer Printouts)
        - Bernie Apol (Box 9)
          - State Legislative Districts (Box 9)
          - State Senate Districts (Box 9)
        - Audit Procedure (Box 9)
        - Eric Baar, House Plan (Box 9)
        - Rosie Board, House Plan-Zero Deviation (Box 9)
        - Rosie Board and A. Robert Kleiner, House Plan Zero Deviation, 4 folders (Box 9)
        - Kim Brace, State Senate Districts (Box 9)
        - Francis Brouillette, State Senate Districts (Box 9)
        - Congressional Plan (Box 9)
        - Democratic, State Senate (Box 9)
        - Existing Districts from 1970, 2 folders (Box 9)
        - A. Robert Kleiner
          - State House (Box 9)
          - State Senate (Box 9)
        - Erma Lurvey, House Plan (Box 9)
        - Bernice Porn and John Cavanagh, Congressional (Box 9)
        - Republican
          - Congressional (Box 10)
          - State House, 3 folders (Box 10)
          - State Senate (Box 10)
          - State House Plan 1 (Box 10)
          - State Senate (Box 10)
          - George Weaver, State Senate (Box 10)
          - Coleman Young and Detroit Branch of NAACP (Box 10)
  - Miscellaneous
    - Apportionment Commission, 3 folders (Box 14)
    - One Binder: "Analysis and 5 Plans Submitted" (Box 14)
    - One Binder: "Committee on Legislative Apportionment" (Box 14)
    - One Binder: "Analysis Plans Presented to Party Leadership, December 6, 1963" (Box 14)
    - Transcripts: Apportionment Meeting of November 15, 1963 and Meeting of Commission on Legislative Apportionment (Lansing), December 31, 1965 (Box 14)
    - Objections to Republican Plans (Box 14)
    - Rough Drafts (Austin-Kleiner Plan) (Box 14)
    - Austin-Kleiner Plan (Box 14)
    - Draft of Oral Argument Before the Michigan Supreme Court March 2, 1964 (Box 14)
    - Correspondence October 1963-February 1964, 3 folders (Box 14)
    - Apportionment Expense (Box 14)
    - Democratic State Central Committee (Apportionment Committee) (Box 14)
    - Kent County Apportionment (Box 14)
- Democratic Party
  The Democratic Party series has been arranged by level of activity: Grand Rapids, Kent County, Fifth Congressional District, State, and National. At the city level there is an undated report on municipal government. County level papers (1969-1979), arranged chronologically, consist of correspondence, minutes of the Kent County Democratic Committee and Executive Committee, and county convention materials. District level papers (1968-1976) consist of chronologically arranged folders containing correspondence, notes on committee meetings, and materials relating to fund raising dinners. There are also papers relating to delegate selection for national conventions (1976-1980) and election analyses by George Weaver (1973-1974).
  For the state level, there are chronological files of correspondence and minutes for the State Central Committee (1965-1981), and papers relating to state conventions (1968-1979). Additionally, there are topical files relating to apportionment, con-con, the Rules and Political Reform Committee, judicial nominations, a party think tank, and a 1978 White House briefing for the Democratic State Party leadership. National Convention files (1964-1980) contain correspondence, caucus minutes, and papers relating to the Michigan Delegation.
  - Grand Rapids Municipal Government in Grand Rapids: A Plan for Action (undated report of Local Government Study Committee) (Box 10)
  - Kent County
    - 1969 (Box 10)
    - 1970, 2 folders (Box 10)
    - 1972 (Box 10)
    - 1974 (Box 10)
    - 1976 (Box 10)
    - 1977 (Box 10)
    - 1978 (Box 10)
    - 1979 (Box 10)
  - Fifth Congressional District
    - 1968-1970 (Box 10)
    - 1974 (Box 10)
    - 1975 (Box 10)
    - 1976 (Box 10)
    - Delegate Selection for National Convention
      - 1976 (Box 10)
      - 1980 (Box 10)
    - Election Analyses by George Weaver 1973-1974 (Box 10)
    - Kent County Democratic Committee, 2 folders (Box 15)
    - Fifth Congressional District Democratic Committee 1973-1978, 8 folders (Box 15)
    - Fifth District Democratic Committee (Patronage) (Box 15)
    - Fifth Congressional District Democratic Organization, 2 folders (Box 16)
    - Fifth District Newsletter (December 1959-September 1962) (Box 16)
    - All Veteran's Housing Committee, Inc (Box 16)
    - "Cross Examination" Television Series, 2 folders
      - 1954-1959 (Box 16)
      - 1956-1958 (Box 16)
  - State
    - Central Committee
      - 1965-1968 (Box 10)
      - 1969 (Box 10)
      - 1970 (Box 10)
      - 1977 (Box 11)
      - 1978 (Box 11)
      - 1979 (Box 11)
      - 1980 (Box 11)
      - 1981 (Box 11)
    - Conventions
      - 1968 (Box 11)
      - 1969 (Box 11)
      - 1970 (Box 11)
      - 1971 (Box 11)
      - 1972 (Box 11)
      - 1973 (Box 11)
      - 1974 (Box 11)
      - 1975 (Box 11)
      - 1977 (Box 11)
      - 1978 (Box 11)
      - 1979 (Box 11)
    - Apportionment 1966 (Box 11)
    - Con-Con
      - 1963 (Box 11)
      - 1976-1977 (Box 11)
    - Correspondence
      - 1961-1968 (Box 11)
      - 1969-1978 (Box 11)
    - Judicial Nominations
      - Michigan Supreme Court 1976 (Box 11)
      - United States District Court (Western Michigan District) 1961 (Box 11)
    - Rules and Political Reform Committee 1975-1978 (Box 11)
    - Think Tank 1973 (Box 12)
    - White House Briefing for Michigan Leadership 1978 (Box 12)
  - National Conventions-Michigan Delegation
    - 1964 (Box 12)
    - 1968 (Box 12)
    - 1976 (Box 12)
    - 1980 (Box 12)
- Photographs
  Photos of the members of the Michigan Commission on Legislative Apportionment; also photos of delegates taken on the floor of the 1964 Democratic National Convention.
  - Commission on Legislative Apportionment (Box 12)
  - Democratic National Convention 1964 (Box 12)
- Scrapbooks
  The Scrapbook series consists of four volumes dated May 1949 -January 1950 and includes clippings about Citizen Action.
  - Citizen Action Scrapbooks May 1949-January 1950, 4 volumes (Box 12)
- Sound Recordings: Cassettes and Tapes
  The Sound Recordings Series includes cassettes and reel-to-reel tapes from 1970 and 1980 apportionment meetings and public hearings, 1963 Con-Con debates, and miscellaneous newscasts, interviews and press conferences relating to Citizen Action, Grand Rapids, and President Gerald R. Ford.
  - Citizen Action 1952 (newscasts, speeches) (Box 13)
  - Commission on Legislative Apportionment, Meetings and Public Hearings
    - 1971-1972 (Box 13)
    - 1981-1982 (Box 13)
  - Con-Con 1963 Debate
    - John B. Martin and A. Robert Kleiner (Box 13)
    - Senator William Leppein and A. Robert Kleiner (Box 13)
  - Miscellaneous radio and television programs
    - Kleiner interviews and press conferences relating to Grand Rapids and Gerald R. Ford circa 1956-1974 (Box 13)
    - Audio-tapes of radio interview program 1952-1960, 25 tapes (Box 13)